<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached to those, who had been scholars of St. Paul's school in Guild-Hall Chapel, London, at their anniversary-meeting on St. Paul's Day, 1678/9 / by W. Wyatt ...</title>
            <author>Wyatt, W. (William), d. 1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12296</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12931361</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12931361</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95682</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67189)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95682)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 995:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached to those, who had been scholars of St. Paul's school in Guild-Hall Chapel, London, at their anniversary-meeting on St. Paul's Day, 1678/9 / by W. Wyatt ...</title>
                  <author>Wyatt, W. (William), d. 1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anniversary sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95682:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95682:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached to thoſe, who had been Scholars of S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> PAUL'S School, IN GUILD-HALL Chapel, LONDON, At their <hi>Anniverſary-Meeting</hi> on St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Day, 1678/9.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. WYATT,</hi> M. A. and Student of <hi>Chriſts-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke,</hi> at the Sign of the Ship in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95682:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95682:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend FATHER in GOD HENRY Lord Biſhop of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the enſuing Diſcourſe might by many more Titles juſtly be ſtil'd your Lordſhip's, yet ſince it was preach'd and made publick under your Lordſhips Government, no Perſon (but your Lordſhip) ought to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied, that I preſume to affix the Name of ſo Great a Patron, to the Dedication. I had the happineſs
<pb facs="tcp:95682:3"/> (though in a lower Sphere) to be known unto your Lordſhip, in a Colledge where I liv'd under your light: I had the advantage to partake of thoſe influences conſtantly diſpers'd and diffus'd by the example of your Nobleſt Education; I there contracted that Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and eſteem for your Lordſhip, which I ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to preſerve and acknowledge; and not this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence alone, but an ambition of being ſheltred under a Name ſo truly Illuſtrious, put me beyond all choice, and in a manner deſtin'd me to this Addreſs. I moſt humbly beg the protection of your Lordſhips Name for an Author newly complemented (againſt his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) into the Preſs, perhaps at firſt not altogether with his will perſwaded into the Pulpit. If your Lordſhip ſhall vouchſafe to favour me ſo far, I ſhall be encouraged to have a better opinion of my perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances in this kind, and I hope to do better. I may without Vanity ſay, I have done ſome things with more accuracy and correctneſs, but there is a fate in Writing, as in men, the ſmaller and moſt inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable are very often preferr'd; and this is the firſt known by my name, and the moſt early Teſtimony
<pb facs="tcp:95682:3"/> I could with any tolerable excuſe (for the occaſion) give the World of my endeavour to expreſs my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt devoted Servant,</hi> William Wyatt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:95682:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95682:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at GUILD-HALL Chappel.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 COR. VIII. 1.</bibl>
               <q>Knowledge puffeth up, but Charity edifieth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great Apoſtle in this Epiſtle ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeverely reprehended, and to no leſs a puniſhment than a total excluſion from happineſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd ſome abominable irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities in the <hi>Corinthian</hi> manners; having declar'd, that Drinking might be acceptable to a <hi>Graecian,</hi> but could not to a Chriſtian's God; that Avarice and Extortion could not purchaſe, nor Thievery break open Heaven; that railings and contemnings would never produce the ſame effects, as Prayers and humiliations; much leſs, that the practices of thoſe ſordid beaſtlineſſes which deſerve not a name among Mankind, could ever approach thoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95682:5"/> pure eyes, which are not able to behold the leaſt iniquity; having branded, I ſay, ſome bruitiſh ſins which Cuſtome had made familiar, and great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples gentile, he proceeds now to an impiety grounded upon, and protected with their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; the occaſion this: <hi>Corinth,</hi> the Metropolis of <hi>Achaia,</hi> and a City ſo haughty, that it contended with <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, (which was the occaſion that L. <hi>Memmius</hi> humbled it to aſhes) was, as all other rich and populous places, exceſſively proud, and to a wonder luxurious. It was the Metropolis of Vice, as well as the Countrey; and grew into a Proverb for Sin, as well as for Beauty and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; its Buildings were far more regular, than its Morals; and there was more Order in their Palaces than in their Lives: Softneſs and Eaſe had expell'd all the thoughts of the laborious exerciſes of Vertue. Pleaſures were their practice, and <hi>Venus</hi> was their Deity, and yet (as it often happens) the men were ingenious, though they were wicked, they retained their Wit, though they loſt their Vertue; they were Men in their underſtandings, though they were Beaſts in their lives; and very good at propoſing, though very ill at practiſing. The beſt were better at a Supper, than a Sermon; yet a general neatneſs and politeneſs of Parts remain'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95682:5"/> among them amidſt all their Senſualities, and they made ſubtile Philoſophers, though impious men: in a word, all the world condemn'd them for their debaucheries, but admir'd them for their endowments. Their delicacies had drawn to them all the looſe that were learned; and there was alwayes among them a conflux of great Wits, as well as great Wickedneſſes; and this was the leading Cauſe, that they were obſtinate againſt, and deaf to all ſober Counſels; this obſtructed all the ways and paſſages by which inſtruction ſhould enter; and their pride ſtill excluded their information. 'Tis in vain to give directions of walking to thoſe who are already conceited that they are in the way: of all Fools, the opinionated are the moſt incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible; 'tis a work of great difficulty to beat them from their holds and faſtneſſes of miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion: there is a double labour with them (as with all wild Creatures) they muſt be tam'd before they are taught: and this was the caſe of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> they were the <hi>Sophi</hi> and the <hi>Virtuoſi</hi> of the World, and who ſhould preſume to teach them that were perfect? What arguments could win upon thoſe, who had already concluded for themſelves, who hated all retractation, who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially determin'd alwayes on their own
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95682:6"/> ſide, and with as much arrogance fixed a note of infallibility upon their own determinations? and what need of edifying to thoſe that had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd themſelves? But St. <hi>Paul</hi> is not one of their irrefragable Society. He tells them, That their Knowledge is the Original of all their Error; that they may ſwell and boaſt as much as they pleaſe, yet they are under a grand miſtake; and the faſter they run, the farther they are out of the way; though through their own falſe Glaſſes they ſeem Giants to themſelves; yet they are but <hi>Puſio's</hi> and Pygmies to thoſe that ſtand in better lights: all their Tumors muſt be diſcuſſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can be in Health: they may be blown up by Knowledge, but they muſt be edified by Charity; for, <hi>Knowledge puffeth up, but Charity edifies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words being plain, eaſie and intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, we ſhall not rack them to make them ſpeak more than they intended. They contain two Affirmative Propoſitions, That <hi>Knowledge puffeth up,</hi> That <hi>Charity edifies men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt; where it will be neceſſary to explain what Knowledge is intended in this place: for Knowledge may have here three ſeveral acceptations.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95682:6"/> 1. If we look upon the words as bearing a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the preceding; <hi>Now as touching things offer'd to Idols, we know that all have knowledge;</hi> then they import thus much, You <hi>Corinthians</hi> upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of your great Knowledge above other men, eſpecially in the caſe of <hi>Idols,</hi> abuſe your libertie, and by eating meat offer'd to Idols in their Temples, you give Scandal to many, and in that ſin your ſelves. You know that <hi>an Idol is nothing,</hi> and we alſo know that <hi>an Idol is nothing in the World;</hi> but you muſt take heed leſt this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of yours become a Stumbling-block to thoſe that are weak. Whilſt you pride your ſelves in your Knowledge, you may Offend your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and whilſt you Offend your Brother, you muſt diſpleaſe your God. Your opinion muſt not make a breach of your love; your Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge muſt give place to your Charity; That may make you proud, but this muſt make you happy. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here in the Text relates to the Hereſie of the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> conſidering that Self-ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was one of the leading Principles in their Divinity, and thoſe Latitudinarians thought no compliance ſinful, by which their Perſons were protected; as alſo if we inquire what My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95682:7"/> of Words they doted on, and what unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible Methods of Science they purſued; how much they did pride themſelves about fruitleſs Genealogies, perplex'd Conjunctions and Poetical Pedigrees; How highly they were elated with the occult Philoſophies of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and empty aerie Speculations about the <hi>Aeones—</hi>by which obſcure Cant and dark wayes of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (as all other Enthuſiaſts) they ſet ſo high a Value upon themſelves, that they contemn'd and ſlighted all the reſt of mankind, looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves as the only <hi>Adepti</hi> of the World, ſcorned and vilified all others both in their Parts and perſons, and as great Monarchs in Learning and Religion, received Laws from none but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; I ſay, if we inquire into this, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they were the only pure as well as the infallible, and thought their Lives Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as well as their Doctrine, St. <hi>Paul</hi> had juſt reaſon to reprehend theſe vain-glorious and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid Scioliſts, and to declare; That Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted not in ſuch Knowledge; that ſcience may make a man vain, but not good; that though they were Gnoſticks by name, they were Ignorants by their practice; and that a little Charity towards an offended Brother was more acceptable in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95682:7"/> eyes of Heaven, and more improv'd a Profeſſor of Chriſtian Religion, than all their Subtile Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rems or thoſe of the Schools of the Philoſophers, or the poſitions of the moſt celebrated Dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers. But</p>
            <p n="3">3. If we look upon the words as independent upon them that go before, and an intire Sentence, without any Relation in themſelves, then they evidently imply thus much, That Knowledge in its utmoſt Latitude is very apt to make the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of it proud and arrogant. The reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of which Propoſition becauſe it contains very much of Truth in it, and by very great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors is taken to be the ſenſe of the place, I ſhall endeavour briefly to evince, and that</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. From the Nature, and conſequently of Mankind.</item>
               <item>2. From the Practice of Mankind.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. There is nothing which the Nature of man is more earneſtly deſirous of than to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Learned; this ambition is rooted in every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual, and there is no perſon ſo ignorant and ſo dull but uſes all the Artifices he can to ſeem inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious. The Clown whoſe education hath not raiſ'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95682:8"/> him to the firſt particles of Words, whoſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet is as unintelligible to him as Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phics, and the conjunction of Syllables as Alge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra; with what wiſdom will he now and then turn over a Book, and look profoundly upon thoſe Characters which make nothing but confus'd im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions upon his Brain? He that can read his own Native language will ſtill be ſpelling at a foreign, and if he Maſters but two or three words of it, he takes or makes all opportunities ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable to ſtammer them forth, and looks upon the parrotting out of ſome futile and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible Elements of ſpeech in a ſtrange tongue, as more of Ornament to him than the diſcourſing a whole day intelligibly and coherently in his own: in all companies what ſtrivings and contentions are there, who ſhould be accounted ſuperiour in readineſs of diſcourſe or ſmartneſs of Wit? one maintains a Paradox to be accounted of a deeper reach than his Neighbour, and with much violence the Fool tires out the aſſeſſors with attempts of making out his contradictious nonſenſe, and being obſtinate to all conviction, the confus'd but irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable creature goes away in Triumph, and is ſatisfied to himſelf that he is the Privie Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of Nature; another ſits gravely and ſpeaks
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95682:8"/> demurely, and very ſuperciliouſly condemns and explodes all other mens Opinions, though he hath no foundation in himſelf to eſtabliſh any of his own: He that is the tendereſt in his Intellectuals, at a meeting is ſtill racking and tormenting himſelf, to put out ſomething that may pleaſe; and when after all the heavings and throes the little ridiculous ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing creeps forth, if it is not acceptable to the height of his expectation, the narrow-ſoul'd wretch breaks out into flame and diſorderly paſſion, and diſturbs and raiſes the company, becauſe he is not reputed the Wiſeſt. There have been more contentious Brawls and Rencounters about precedency of Knowledge, than that of Place: Honour is as tender in the Matter of Wit, as that of Courage; and the Word <hi>Fool</hi> draws forth the Sword as ſwiftly, as that of <hi>Coward:</hi> that ignominious term brings with it a Degrada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſomething beneath the Dignity of his being; it levels him to the <hi>Aſs</hi> and the <hi>Mule, that have no underſtanding.</hi> Some men have had the Patience to hear their Family, but very few have ſuffer'd their Reaſon, to be abus'd. You may with more ſafety deſpiſe any part
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95682:9"/> of a mans blood, than that which is elabora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Spirits for his Brain. Since then Knowledge is of ſo ineſtimable a value among Mortals, and of all the infinity of Pretenders to it, there are ſo very few that attain to an indifferent portion of it; certainly thoſe who upon ſolid Principles of Reaſon are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, that they are able to foil and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance others in the contentions of Wit and courſes of Learning, muſt be of a miraculous temper, if they do not pride themſelves in their own ſtrength and ſwiftneſs, and highly contemn the infirmity and ſlowneſs of others. Superiority in all caſes puffs men up: He that is ſeated above, looks down with ſcorn and diſdain at thoſe at his feet; and he that knows moſt, makes his inſolent Triumphs upon the Weakneſs of another. Every man without a Flatterer, hath a very great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for himſelf: Self-love is as univerſal as mankind. There is no man but carries his Darling about him: his own Sayings are all Oracle, and his Actions, Wonder. The Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations of a Market, and a prudent Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; the Intrigues of a Pariſh, and the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Veſtry, hath many times made men
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95682:9"/> look big and ſtately over their brethren, leſs employ'd in ſuch grand and intricate affairs, made them contemn all others in their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts, and think themſelves the only Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Heads, and the fitteſt Materials to make Miniſters of State. As for thoſe who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſo, and deſerve that title by a natural acuteneſs, conſtant exerciſe in great buſineſs, and long obſervations of the events of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in humane Actions: with what proud State and Grandeur, they rule the more ignorant and inferiour Officers! How do they over-look Suppliants! What offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings muſt be paid, before you can come to the Grandee himſelf! What kind of belea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guering there muſt be of a man! What ſlow and regular approaches muſt be made, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can have any hopes to take him in! let them enquire who are the Followers of Courts, and Hunters of Fortune. And 'twere very well, if the ill effects of Knowledge did not appear any where elſe. True it is, that knowledge puffs men up, as well as riches: without them it can make a man proud, but in conjunction with them, it is commonly in ſufferable.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95682:10"/>
            <p> We come now to ſpeak ſomething to the Practice of men in this particular: and,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. We ſhall ſpeak of the Antient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers. And,</item>
               <item>2. Of ſome ſince Chriſtianity began. And,</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. If we look among the Ancient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, with what ſtrange dogmaticalneſs did they lay down all their Poſitions! How im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious were they in their Concluſions! How earneſtly did they endeavour to tye down Mans free Reaſon to their narrow Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples! and aſpire to a Dominion over mens ſouls, more eagerly than the worſt of Tyrants ever did over that of their bodies! They gave another interpretation to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and improv'd it into ſelf-conceit and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance. How did they plume up, and ſwell themſelves upon every little invention! Nay, their pride oftentimes tranſported them into fooliſh, and ſometimes into Tragical At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts. If <hi>Pythagoras</hi> hit luckily upon the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of a Problem, as if the World were made by it for ever happy, an Hecatomb falls for ſacrifice, not ſo much in Gratitude to the Gods, as to raiſe a Value upon the Worth of the Inventor. An unexpected Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95682:10"/> and the glory of lighting upon it, makes <hi>Archimedes</hi> run naked, bawling out his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> through the ſtreets; and his Knowledge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſts him of his Shame. But theſe are things which perhaps may be ſubjects of mirth, and might pleaſe in Comoedy. But when an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedocles</hi> ſhall hurl himſelf into the flames of <hi>Aetna,</hi> becauſe he cannot explore the cauſes from whence proceed thoſe Fountains of Burnings, and inexhauſtible ſources of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur: or when the great <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf, (I ſpeak according to <hi>Juſtin Martyr;</hi> for <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes Laertius</hi> and <hi>Dion. Halicar.</hi> give another account) ſhall tumble himſelf into the Sea, becauſe his mind is not vaſter than that, and cannot comprehend the Nature of it; we ought to deplore that inſufferable Pride which an inquiſition into the Nature of things brings along with it, which drives men into ſuch deſperate Attempts, that they endeavour to be nothing, becauſe they cannot be Gods. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable almoſt are the Inſtances of this nature which might be produced: inſomuch, that if a true account could be taken, as the Vanity of Sciences might make one of the beſt; ſo the Pride of the Scioliſts would make
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95682:11"/> one of the moſt Voluminous Books of the world. What made thoſe Numerous Sects and Diviſions amongſt them? What cauſe can be aſſign'd of their being minc'd into ſeveral Factions and Conventicles, but only Pride, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd by an opinion of Excellency in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? This form'd them into different Claſſes and Congregations; made them wear di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctive beards and habits; every one had a badge of his Order, and look'd very oddly upon any one that wore not the ſame Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. Their Principles and their Dictates ſeem alwayes to be fram'd, rather to oppoſe, than to eſtabliſh; and they are not ſo eager in ſearching after truth, as in ſerving their Hypotheſis. Nay, when ſometimes an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Reconciliator might eaſily have made them ſpeak the ſame things; and perhaps there might be ſomething of Truth in both; yet they were ſtill obſtinate in not underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, ſtill perplex'd the matter with abſtruſe Subtilties and nice Speculations, with new coin'd words and phraſes, which were ſure to keep them at diſtance enough; and they dar'd do any thing, rather than hearken to an accommodation; leſt the firſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95682:11"/> Propoſer ſhould be thought to give up the cauſe to his imagin'd adverſary. Thus the maintaining a Party, ſtill kept up quarrels and diſſentions among them, and their whole Lives was nothing elſe but a ſtate of War: no Rivals in Empire or Love ever more mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally hated one another, than the <hi>Stoick</hi> did the <hi>Epicurean,</hi> or the <hi>Cynic</hi> all; they flew from one another, as men do from a Plague; thought one anothers Breath contagious; and there was not more difference in their Doctrines, than in their Diſpoſitions. The <hi>Stoick</hi> was a Creature of Paradoxes, a very formal piece of Hypocriſie: He was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly the <hi>Phariſee</hi> of <hi>Greece;</hi> his pace was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn; and the longer was his beard, the more he preſum'd was in his head: he had kept all the commandments of Virtue, or rather commanded Virtue from his Youth: he had odd Expoſitions on the Laws of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality and Nature; he talk'd of nothing but high rants of her; and his diſcourſe was ſtill of perfection: he think'd the Gods, that he was not like other men; for he was not only not guilty of all Vice, but of all Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He was feated forſooth above all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95682:12"/> thoſe Storms and Tempeſts that rowl in the breaſt of Humane Nature: and yet after all this extravagant boaſting, there was ſo much turpitude found in the lives of moſt of his Sect, that by ſome more civil, though not ſo ſupercilious men, they paſſed into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and a Proverb. The <hi>Epicurean</hi> (or at leaſt, <hi>Epicurus</hi> himſelf) was frugal, ſober and temperate enough; but then having gayer Principles, was a man of more refin'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: his Brow was not contracted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Wrinkles, nor his Mind into Moroſeneſs: there was an even ſtilneſs in his life, like that of Nature in the World, whoſe operations he beſt made out, and whoſe beauties he contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But thus they lived with different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and irreconcileable Opinions; wrote much of Friendſhip, but practis'd none; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd pride in their Books, and made it Canonical by their Examples. Nay, if ever Fortune brought them to a conference, their paſſion ſtill quite extinguiſh'd their reaſon; their Diſputes ended in Reproaches: and that might very well be, if it is true as one ſayes, <hi>Qui autem unquam ex Philoſophis Virtutem propter ſe expetendam maxime contenderunt, tantâ arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95682:12"/> 
               <hi>inflati fuerunt, ut appareat non ob aliud Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem expetiiſſe quàm ut ſuperbiendi haberent ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I paſs now to the times of Chriſtianity: and here we find Antichriſt working in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dawn of it. The pride of the <hi>Gnoſtick</hi> made the firſt Hereſie; and the plainneſs and ſimplicity of the Goſpel, was that which made the eſteem'd learned World oppoſe it. In all Ages ambition or ſelf-conceitedneſs hath rais'd perſecutions, and fram'd diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: a <hi>Julian,</hi> a <hi>Lucian,</hi> or an <hi>Hierocles,</hi> were men too gallant in their own opinion to ſtoop to the dictates of Fiſhermen: the Maſter's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing crucified, was <hi>one</hi> great cauſe that his Doctrines were not received: and thoſe which for ſo many years had been poring after, and tracing <hi>Cabbaliſtick</hi> myſteries in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, mightily deſpis'd that more great one of Godlineſs; and ſought both by their ſwords and pens to eradicate that Religion, which ſtill grew the faſter for its members being prun'd. For the Sword did rather prune, than root out; and ſtill new Armies aroſe from the ſlain: there was a kind of ſeminal principle in the primitive Chriſtians Blood;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95682:13"/> and their very graves were prolifique; ſo that after ſo many Volumes of Satyrs, ſevere Edicts and mercileſs proſcriptions, it was confeſs'd, that Chriſtianiſm was no more to be expell'd the World, than Light. When the greateſt Fences and Banks were thrown up againſt it, it ſtill inſenſibly gain'd upon them; and at laſt like an uncontrollable Sea over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd all oppoſitions, carried all things along with it in the inundation; and againſt all the trifling Machinations of weak, but malicious Humane Nature, prov'd it ſelf the Child of Heaven, the Salvation of Mankind, and the Ruine of its Oppoſers. 'Tis an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> or a <hi>Socinus</hi> that makes the deepeſt wounds in Communion: that is, men elated with a ſtrange opinion of their own worth, whoſe knowledge hath ſcrew'd them up to the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing upon nice points and ſubtil Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: and rather than think with the Vulgar, they will blaſpheme the Nature they cannot comprehend; involve the World into eternal diſputes, and themſelves into as du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable miſeries, a <hi>Scaligers</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (though in it ſelf no great matter) puffs him up into a whole period of Commendation of himſelf;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95682:13"/> and indeed the whole race of Criticks had a particular paſſion for themſelves: his Son contemn'd mankind, and <hi>Schioppius</hi> him: <hi>Lipſius</hi> more often comments in praiſe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, than his Author: and <hi>Salmaſius</hi> rather than be thought to be confuted, flyes into the face of that moſt Venerable and Sacred perſon Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> whoſe almoſt only knowledge not puff'd him up, and ſcurrilouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affronts him with the meaneſt of Wit, ill language; whoſe Name ſhall flouriſh, and piety be rever'd, when whole Armies of the little ſawcy Grammarians ſhall rot into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſs, and lye unregarded buried in Duſt and Oblivion. It would be too great an injury to your patience, and no very pleaſant la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to my ſelf, to preſent you with all the dirt and filth interſpers'd in Authors famous enough for Learning, and as infamous for the concomitant of it, Pride. How many Volumes are there in the World, whoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is little elſe but breach of Charity? How many great Authors Ink makes nothing but blots upon anothers name? and endeavours to ſend them down foul to poſterity? How few Replications are there, which carry not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95682:14"/> poyſon in them to the Reputation of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd? From all which inſtances and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we may very well gather, that knowledge is commonly a troubleſome thing to others, and of a fermenting nature in the perſon that poſſeſſes it; and however it may aggrandize a man as to himſelf, yet really his ſwelling is his diſeaſe; and he may be puff'd up by Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but 'tis Charity that edifies, the next thing briefly to be conſider'd. And here ſhould I ſpeak of Charity in its full extent and Latitude, I might include in it all the Duties of Chriſtian Religion. I intend to ſpeak of it briefly: and 1. In General: 2. In particular, as it relates to private perſons or Societies.</p>
            <p>1. In General. And as ſo, 'tis the nobleſt and the ſweeteſt of Graces: Charity is the Chriſtian Name for Love: by this I have a kindneſs and reſpect for all mankind; and the bounds of my Charity extend as far as thoſe of the Sun: by this I pity the poor <hi>Indian, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> or <hi>Turk</hi> that dyes in torments by the too ſevere ſentence of a mercileſs Governour; and I could wiſh, there were no Tyrants in the World, though I live out of the reach of their long hands, am far enough disjoyn'd from the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95682:14"/> injuſtice of their commands, and the ſeverity of their rage: my good wiſhes reach as far, and my prayers enlarge themſelves to the extenſion of the Univerſe. By Charity and mutual Love, by what firm bands might Societies be joyn'd? 'twould bring down the converſation of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon Earth, and plant a conſtant Peace and Serenity here, in ſome degree like that which the bleſſed enjoy above. Friendſhip (which is one of the moſt beautiful things in the World) is but Charity contracted: and though the rayes may burn fiercer, yet they loſe the glories of expanſion and diffuſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Charity veils over the fault of an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Brother, and hath mercy upon fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and infirmities; becauſe it conſiders, that Error ſticks as cloſe to man, as his Nature. 'Tis the Devils property, to be Malicious; and his moſt glorious appellation is, that of <hi>Accuſer.</hi> In all that incomparable Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um of Charity in the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> there can nothing be ſaid of it greater, than that <hi>Charity ſuffereth long, and is kind, and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things.</hi> There is ſomething looks di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine in pardoning: and 'tis an attribute of the Deity, to be <hi>long-ſuffering.</hi> Charity then
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95682:15"/> lifts us near to Heaven, and aſſimilates us to that God, who is infinite in forbearing. In a word, 'tis Charity that may make us happy here, and muſt crown us hereafter. Let then the fooliſh Pretenders to the Wiſdom of this World, grow as big as they pleaſe with whimſical Notions of Globules, Vortices and Atoms, let them dote on a Diagram, and be never ſo deeply immers'd in Number; let them have the <hi>tongue of men and Angels, if they have not Charity,</hi> they are in the Apoſtles phraſe, <hi>as ſounding braſs, and the tinkling cymbal:</hi> things of more noiſe, than uſe: which ſhine, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, but have not any great Reputation for ſolid Worth. 'Tis Charity, and not great Words and phantaſtick Hypotheſes, that muſt ſet a luſtre upon all our actions. Heaven is not to be gain'd by proud looks and arrogant ſuppoſitions; but by a conſtant Tenour of bountifulneſs in our Lives, and integrity in our Actions. He much miſtakes his Creation, that thinks, he was made for no other End, than to reflect upon, and admire, and careſs himſelf. That <hi>new commandment</hi> of <hi>loving one another,</hi> muſt be ſedulouſly obey'd: the ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Good, muſt conſtantly ſtream forth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95682:15"/> to our Neighbour; and we cannot any way attain to our own happineſs, unleſs we be tender of his. The way of Charity is an eaſie and a noble way to bleſſedneſs.</p>
            <p>Since then Charity is ſo highly accepted of Heaven, and ſo beneficial to Men, how great and glorious is it in thoſe which endeavour the propagation of it to Numbers? place it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the narrow confines of an Houſhold; and as much as in them lyes, ſtrive to dilate its Empire, and make it coextenſive to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Now though this Univerſal Charity is every mans duty, yet there is another Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, the Second thing to be conſider'd; for ſince 'tis impoſſible this Univerſal ſhould have any real effect over all the World; that is, I may love all men, but cannot be acquainted with, or at hand to help them; therefore men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways though they do not bound, yet they more evidence their Charity according to Relations or Conjunctions, which ariſe either from Blood, Society or Converſe: and indeed eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man (without any injury to Religion) is ſo much Lord of his own Charity, as to chooſe the chiefeſt object of it. 'Tis true, that I muſt love my Neighbour, and every man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95682:16"/> is ſo; but certainly without offence, I may more encline to him, by whoſe Wiſdom I am inſtructed, or by whoſe Bounty ſupported; I may ſelect him for my Companion before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who beſt ſuites with my humour, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it be not vicious; and the Benefits or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Gayneſſes of Life, are Cauſes enough for preference in Election. I know there are ſome Men of more Envy, than Wit or Wiſdom, that eſteem ſuch Meetings and Feaſts of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as theſe we this day celebrate, as the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Pride, and the Parents of Separation in a Community; that think Men by thus doing, eſteem much better of themſelves, than of others; and ſuppoſe they make a League againſt all others, whilſt they make one of Friendſhip among themſelves; and what is only Concord, they name Conſpiracy. But let ſuch men know, that whilſt they pretend a Breach of Charity in others, they make an extreamly wide one themſelves; and for want of line to ſound the true depth of things, like all Zealots, they grow Malicious, whilſt they would approve themſelves Inſtructers. But we are not at this time more bound to ſatisfie their ignorance, than to love it: Certainly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95682:16"/> there cannot be any more Natural Cauſe for the uniting Men into the Conjunctions of Love and Charity, than a Similitude in Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: the ſames Rules and Principles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce moſt commonly the ſame Manners, and in ſpite of Buſineſs and all the other avocations of humane life, ſomething will remain of what was formerly imbib'd. We ſee men of the greateſt Buſineſs, Wiſdom and Grandeur ſtill recollecting what they acted in their firſt days, and then bringing in ſome Perſon, whoſe Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity then, was perhaps the Greateſt Cauſe of a Friendſhip now. If then Likeneſs and Congruity may be admitted to be the Cauſes of Friendſhip and Love; and ſimilitude of Education is the moſt apt to produce that; we have all the reaſon in the World firmly to link our ſelves into a Society, whoſe firſt meeting together, ſprang from ſo great a Cauſe, and hath ſince produc'd ſo good effects of Friendſhip. I know there are ſome indeed whoſe neither Wit or Manners could ever prove that they had been in a School; who are alwayes traducing, not only the Method, but the Authors of their education: and of ſuch, the next ſubject will be their Parents, and the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95682:17"/> next their God: But certainly all ſober men muſt acknowledge, that they deſerve exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly well of the Publick, that can make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo miſerable, as to labour in the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Youth: the Toil is theirs, though the fruit be Ours: And yet let the beſt Man here ſink into himſelf, and he will ſoon confeſs, that if he had followed ſtrictly thoſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples he brought with him from School, he had been much a better Chriſtian, though not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a Richer Man than he is. 'Tis not the fault of a <hi>Seneca,</hi> but of <hi>Nero</hi> himſelf, that he proves wicked. Let us all labour to live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the practical Principles, at leaſt, which were inſtill'd into us within thoſe Walls, and make that place henceforward as immortal by our Piety, as ſome have done already by their Learned Parts. Let us imitate the action of the great Apoſtle in this day; and if any Man hath been a Perſecutor of his Saviour (as every Sinner is) the greater his Malice hath prov'd, the ſooner let him return, and appear the more faithful Servant to his abuſed Lord. Let our Charity to one another encreaſe, as the Years grow more numerous upon us; and in this innocent Cuſtom continue, till Years
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95682:17"/> ſhall looſe themſelves into Eternity: other Actions perhaps may proclaim us Great, but this will declare us Good. Let others upon very ſtrange Principles (as much as they pleaſe) think Rebellion Meritorious, and Murder Lawful; Canonize the Authors of Diſcord, and make Traytors Saints: but let us ſhew our ſelves Chriſtians by thoſe Nobler ways of Unity, Concord, Peace and Love, and then our Great Maſter (who was himſelf the Miracle of Charity) will lead us into thoſe Serene and Bleſſed Places, where Love reigns in its full perfection, and a conſtant Unity and Concord makes Heaven. Let us put up our Prayers then to Almighty God, that He would continue in us this Gift of Charity, the very Bond of Peace; that in helping, ſuſtaining and doing Kindneſſes one for another here, we may lye down in the Arms of the Eternal Love hereafter.</p>
            <p>Now to God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcrib'd as is moſt due, all Glory, Honour, Praiſe, Might, Majeſty and Dominion now and for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Love of God and the Fellowſhip of the Holy Ghoſt, be with you all.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
